Guide to the Tully Family Papers
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
Tully Family Papers
1667-1915
Ms Coll 40
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
1.5
(3 boxes)
William Tully (1785-1859) was professor of materia medica and therapeutics at the Medical Institution of Yale College from 1824 to 1842. The collection contains a small amount of correspondence by or to Tully and limited material on Tully's medical career. One subseries concerns settling the estate of William Tully and finding funds to support his daughters Sarah and Elizabeth. The collection contains genealogies, original documents of the Tully family in Connecticut, and also documents related to ancestors of Tully's wife, Mary Potter Tully, particularly her father, the Rev. Elam Potter, and her stepfather, the Rev. Nehemiah Prudden. Photographs include daguerrotypes of Tully's children.
Tully, William, 1785-1859
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Harry B. Ferris, M.D., professor of anatomy at Yale University School of Medicine, obtained this material in 1930 along with some of Tully's furniture from the woman who let rooms to Elizabeth Tully in Springfield, Massachusetts, before her death in 1915. He donated the papers to the Beaumont Medical Club in 1934. They are on permanent deposit in the Historical Library.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Some items are too fragile to copy.
Biographical / Historical
William Tully was born on November 18, 1785, the son of Colonel William and Eunice Tully of Saybrook, Connecticut. He graduated from Yale College in 1806. In the spring of 1807, Tully began studying medicine with Mason F. Cogswell of Hartford and in the fall of that year traveled to New Hampshire to study medicine with Nathan Smith at Dartmouth College. Upon his return to Connecticut in 1810, Tully studied under Samuel Carter and entered the office of Eli Ives, later professor of materia medica at Yale. Tully was licensed to practice by the Connecticut Medical Society in 1810 and opened an office in Enfield, Connecticut in 1811. In 1813, he married Mary Potter of Enfield. Tully lived and practiced for several years in Middletown, Connecticut, where he co-authored with Dr. Thomas Miner a book, Essays on Fevers, and Other Medical Subjects (1823). From 1824 to 1830 he was president and professor of medical practice and jurisprudence at the Vermont Academy of Medicine, in Castleton, Vermont. While at Castleton he was appointed professor of materia medica and therapeutics at the Medical Institution of Yale College and moved to New Haven; however he remained on the staff of the Vermont Academy until 1838. Tully resigned his chair at Yale in 1842 and eventually moved to Springfield, Massachusetts, where he lived with his two unmarried daughters, Sarah and Elizabeth. He continued his practice and taught at the Berkshire Medical Institution in Pittsfield, Massachusetts. Late in his career, he published Materia Medica, or Pharmacology and Therapeutics (1857-58). He died in Springfield in on February 28, 1859, predeceased by his wife and survived by only three of their eleven children, Sarah, William, and Elizabeth. Sarah and Elizabeth continued to live together in Springfield after their father's death.
The Tully family came to New England from England in the 1640s. Tully's grandfather, William Tully of Saybrook married Elizabeth Lay and had three daughters and a son, Col. William Tully (1758-1811). Col. Tully married his cousin Eunice Tully (1758-1815) and had only one child, William Tully (1785-1859) who became a physician. Dr. William Tully's wife, Mary Potter (1791-1853), was the daughter of the Rev. Elam Potter (1742-1794) of Enfield and Sibyl Pease Potter (1754-1822). Some time after 1799, Sybil Potter was married again to the Rev. Nehemiah Prudden of Enfield, then a widower.
Scope and Contents
The collection is comprised of a small amount of personal correspondence of William Tully, memoranda, receipts, and wills. There is considerable material on the settling of Tully's estate, especially correspondence of the executor, Dr. Edwin Seeger. Seeger and others arranged for the sale of Tully's books by auction and tried to have his manuscripts (now unlocated) published. Among the estate papers are notes on patients who still owed money to Tully. The correspondence of Sarah and Elizabeth Tully in the collection mostly concerns the estate, financial matters, and family. The family part of the collection relates to the ancestry of the Tully, Potter, Pease, and Prudden families. There are Tully land deeds going back to the seventeenth century, a Bible signed by "John Tulley" in 1667, notes on scriptures by the Rev. Elam Potter, and two sermons by the Rev. Nehemiah Prudden of Enfield, as well as genealogical material and early documents related to the families. Photographs include twelve daguerrotypes of Tully's children, including of Hephzibah Tully who died in 1849.
Arrangement
Organized in four series: 1. William Tully (1785-1859) and immediate family. 2. Tully family ancestors. 3. Potter, Pease, and Prudden families. 4. Photographs and miscellany.
Administration of estates -- Connecticut -- 19th century; Genealogy -- Tully; Materia medica; Medicine -- Connecticut; Saybrook (Conn.); Daguerreotypes (photographs); Deeds -- Connecticut -- 19th century; Deeds -- Connecticut -- 18th century; Deeds -- Connecticut -- 17th century; Sermons; Photographs; Wills; Physicians -- Connecticut; Herrick, Edward Claudius, 1811-1862; Potter, Elam, 1742-1794; Potter family; Pruden family; Prudden, Nehemiah, 1749-1815; Edwin Seeger, 1811-1866; Tully, Elizabeth, 1830-1915; Tully, Sarah, 1817-1901; Tully, William, 1785-1859; Tully family -- Genealogy; George A. Leavitt & Co; Yale College (1718-1887). Medical Institution; Yale University. School of Medicine
- William Tully (1785-1859) and immediate family, 1.
- Correspondence, Writings, Receipts, Subseries 1
  - Letters by William Tully, 1835-1858 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Letter, New Haven, to [Dr. Cornelius S. Baker], 1835 January 3
      Scope and Contents
      Draft of a letter to a suitor to one of his daughters. The recipient is probably Dr. Cornelius S. Baker who later married Tully's daughter, Eunice, on January 26, 1836.
    - To Dr. Hazen, Middletown - typed transcript of a letter, 1855 April 24
      On making Tully's Compound Powder of Camphor as a substitute for Dover's Powder. Tully does not know which Middletown Hazen is from, but sends his letter to Middletown, Connecticut. The original letter is not in the collection.
    - Letter, Pittsfield, Massachusetts, to Edwin Seeger, M.D., Springfield, Massachusetts, 1858 October 11
      Tully is in Pittsfield, Massachusetts. Letter discusses his giving lectures and whether the students are prepared well enough by Dr. Childs. Discusses his own health.
  - Letters to William Tully, 1833-1859 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - From Daniel Bontecue, Springfield, 1833 April 8
      To Tully in New Haven on the death of Tully's daughter Catherine and the death of his own daughter.
    - From Cornelius L. Baker, "Churchville", 1835 January 18
      To Tully in New Haven regarding his daughter Eunice Tully.
    - From S. M. Tully, Saybrook, 1837 February 11
      Sends Mr. Pratt's acount.
    - From J. Barnes, Middletown, 1838 February 21
      To Tully in New Haven concerning accounts.
    - From Edward C. Herrick, New Haven, 1853 December 2
      Herrick handled legal affairs for the Tully family. He requests information on the type of stone and inscription for the grave, probably for Mary Tully, Dr. Tully's wife, who died in September 1853.
    - R. E. Pratt, Saybrook, to William Tully, 1858 January 25
      Financial and personal.
    - From J. Branch, "Abbeville", 1859 December 19
      Is replying belatedly to Tully's letter. A physician friend will visit Tully in Springfield. Tully had died February 28, 1859.
    - From T. F. Welch, Milford, n.d.
      Concerning a prescription that Tully gave him.
    - From Frances A. Clarke, n.d.
      Incomplete letter with envelope addressed to William Tully in Springfield "per Miss Elizabeth L. Tully." On reverse is a pencil transcription from the tombstone of the Rev. Elam Potter (1742-1794), father of William Tully's wife.
  - Early documents concerning Mary Potter Tully, wife of Dr.William Tully, 1810-1814 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Legal document of money owed by Elam O. Potter to Mary Tully, 1810 February 5
      Elam O. Potter was Mary Potter Tully's brother. William Tully wrote on the document,"This bond is cancelled by a transfer of these shares. Wm Tully." He referred to stock of the Hartford Bank.
    - Certification by Nehemiah Prudden, rector of the church in Enfield, that Mrs. Mary Tully is a member in good standing, 1814 June 13
    - Survey of the division of the property of the estate of Capt. Ephraim Pease, Enfield, 1814 May 20
      "Copy" but appears contemporary. Capt. Pease was Mary Tully's grandfather. One portion went to William and Mary Tully.
  - Thomas Miner and William Tully, An Examination of the Strictures in the New England Journal for October, 1823 and in the North American Reviwew... on Essays on Fevers, & c. (Middletown, CT: Printed by E. & H. Clarke, 1823) (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Pamphlet in response to the published critiques of Thomas Miner and William Tullly, Essays on Fevers and Other Medical Subjects (Middletown, CT: Printed and published by E. & H. Clark, 1823).
  - "Books taken for Yale College", 1844 September (Box 1, Folder 5)
    List of books with prices. Presumably Tully sold some of his books to Yale.
  - Agreeement with Jefferson Church of Springfield, Massachusetts, to publish Tully's book on materia medica, 1852 November 18 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    William Tully's Materia medica; or, Pharmacology and therapeutics, 2 vols. was published by J. Church, Springfield in 1857-1858. Tully transferred copyright to Church.
  - Miscellaneous memoranda by William Tully, 1830s and n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Mostly financial.
  - William Tully receipts, 1825-1839 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Some receipts relate to the deaths of Sarah Tully (sister of grandfather) in 1830 and of Catherine Tully (daughter) in 1833.
  - William Tully receipts, 1849-1859 and n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Includes three bills for money owed by patients, 1851-1856. See also Box 1, folder 13.
  - Will of Mary Tully, New Haven (Copy) and other materials concerning her death, 1851 April 7 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Mary Tully, wife of Dr. William Tully, died September 8, 1853. The copy of her will left the residue of her personal property to Edward C. Herrick, New Haven, to be held by him in trust for her surviving children, Sarah, Elizabeth Lay, and William. Also includes "Estate of Mrs. Mary Tully in Account with L. A. Thomas," n.d.; and "Edwd. C. Herrick, trustee of estate of Mary Tully," n.d.
  - Wills of William Tully, 1849-1857 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    His will of December 14, 1857 left his property to his three surviving children, Sarah, Elizabeth, and William. Edwin Seeger, M.D. of Springfield was appointed executor.
- William Tully's estate and his immediate family, Subseries 2
  William Tully M.D. died February 28, 1859 in Springfield, Massachusetts, where he was living with his two daughters, Sarah (1817-1901) and Elizabeth (1830-1915). He was also survived by a son, William (1830-1880), who married in 1860. The settling of Tully's estate is well documented in these papers. Though William received some assets, the overwhelming concern was to find enough money to support the two unmarried daughters throughout their lives.
  - Monies owed by and to the estate of William Tully, 1859-1860 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    These bills were collected by Edwin Seeger, M.D. of Springfield, Tully's executor. Included is a list of money donated to Sarah and Elizabeth Tully in memory of William Tully, by various people including Yale medical professors.
  - Money owed to the estate by patients of William Tully (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Included are eight bills for medical visits and treatments by Tully and a list of patients owing money. These cover the period 1851-1857. Annotations in pencil state whether payment will be received.
  - Letters of Edward C. Herrick to Edwin Seeger concerning the estate of William Tully, 1859-1861 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Concerns a catalogue of Tully's library that Herrick had prepared, and plans for the sale of Tully's books.
  - Letters of George A. Leavitt & Co., Auctioneers, to Edwin Seeger, 1859-1860 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Concerns the auction of William Tully's books in New York. Beinecke Library holds a copy of the sale catalog. See Catalogue of an extensive collection of scientific, medical and miscellaneous books, being the private library of the late Dr. Wm. Tully ...: which will be sold at auction ... (New York: George A. Leavitt & Co., [1859])
  - Letters of Henry F. Fish, Waterbury, and F. L. Fish to Edwin Seeger, 1859-1862 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Henry F. Fish and his successors were insurers and friends of the Tully family. There are two letters from Henry F. Fish to George A. Leavitt & Co. Henry F. Fish hoped to obtain money for the estate from the publication of Tully's manuscripts.
  - Other letters to Edwin Seeger, executor, 1859-1860 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    From S. B. Baker, William R. Clarke, Hampden Fire Insurance Co., Samuel Noyes, and R. E. Pratt, Lucas A. Thomas, H. A. Tilden, and Sarah Tully.
  - Marriage certificate of William Tully and Elizabeth King of New London, 1860 March 14 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Plus contemporary copy.
  - Letters of Edward C. Herrick to Mary Tully, and then to Sarah and Elizabeth Tully, 1852-1862 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Letters concern income from property he is managing from the estates of Mary Tully and later William Tully.
  - Letters of Fish & Lee, Myron H. Fish, and William T. Fish to Sarah and Elizabeth Tully, 1859-1861, 1867 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    The letters are partly financial and partly personal. One letter is on Aetna letterhead.
  - Letters of L.Watson, M.D. to Sarah Tully concerning possible publication of William Tully's manuscripts, 1868-1869 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Includes a circular by Henry F. Fish, Waterbury, requesting Tully manuscripts for the purpose. His manuscripts do not seem to have been published.
  - Letters to Sarah and Elizabeth Tully, 1861-1886 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Also included are a few financial memoranda, 1870-1878.
  - Draft will of Sarah Tully and report of estate by Elizabeth Tully, executrix, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Sarah Tully died in 1901. The draft will is undated. There is also an unsigned draft by Sarah Tully appointing Myron H. Fish her attorney, 1858.
  - Letters, postcards, and greeting cards to Elizabeth Tully, 1909-1913 and n.d. (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Letters to Elizabeth Tully and materials from religious institutions, 1906-1915 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Elizabeth Tully bank accounts and stock investments, 1898-1906 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Includes circulars to stockholders from the Consolidated Alaskan Co., 1900-1904, the Springfield Street Railway Co., 1900, and other companies.
  - Newspaper clippings, religious poetry, and miscellanea (Box 1, Folder 27)
    The clippings and religious poetry were presumably collected by Elizabeth Tully. They include some newspaper obituaries.
- Tully family ancestors, 2.
- Tully family genealogy, Subseries 1
  Members of the Tully family came from England to New England in 1646 or 1647. Dr. William Tully's grandfather, William Tully, married Elizabeth Lay and had three daughters and a son, also William. This Col. William Tully of Saybrook (1759-1811) married his cousin Eunice Tully (1758-1815) in 1785 and had only one child, Dr. William Tully (1785-1859).
  - "Tully Record": genealogy of the Tully family, 19th century. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    This bound journal was written in the nineteenth century. William Tully's death (1859) and the death of his son William (1880) and daughter Sarah (1901) were added later in pencil, probably by his daughter Elizabeth, whose death in 1915 is not noted. Includes note from H. B. Ferris on the provenance of this book.
  - Tully family genealogy by William Tully, M.D., 19th century (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Also an additional genealogical list in pencil.
  - Notes on early Tully genealogy, ca. 1880 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    On the early history of the Tully family, written in response to an article in the New Haven Palladium, 1880, on documents found in Fanueil Hall, Boston. Author is not identified.
  - Tully family graves (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Information and inscriptions on graves, each written as separate notes. Some of these notes were written by Dr. William Tully. Includes a partial key to the family graves at Grove Street Cemetery, New Haven.
- Early Tully family documents, Subseries 2
  - Bible owned and signed by "John Tulley," London, 1667, 1667 or before (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Printed Bible is missing its title page and is unidentified. In back is a note of the donation of the Bible to the Medical Library by Mrs. H. B. Ferris, 1941. Inserted is a small needlework of a church.
  - Deed from Robert Lay of Saybrook to "John Tulley" of Saybrook, 1680 February 7 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - "John Tulley, Sr." of Saybrook, to Mr. Harris, 1693/94 February 23 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Concerning books that Harris sent him. Tulley requested an almanac.
  - Will of William Tully of Saybrook, 1769 September 5 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    He appears to have died in 1775. Will signed by John and Samuel Tully.
  - Special town meeting, Saybrook, 1777 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    On soldiers and ammunition for the Revolutionary War and on division of property. The Tullys are not mentioned.
  - Letters from William Tully, Saybrook, to his sister Hephzibah Tully, 1793 September (Box 2, Folder 10)
    2 items. This William Tully was Dr. William Tully's father. He writes to his sister on the illness and death of their mother, Elizabeth Lay Tully. The second letter also contains a letter to Joseph Utley requesting that he come to Saybrook on behalf of Elisha Utley who is dangerously ill. William asks Hephzibah to convey the message.
  - Tully family deeds, 1746-1859 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Some of the deeds relate to Dr. William Tully.
- Potter, Pease, and Prudden families, 3.
  This series relates to the ancestors of Dr. William Tully's wife, Mary Potter Tully (1791-1853), particularly the Potter, Prudden families. Mary Tully was the daughter of the Rev. Elam Potter and Sybil Pease Potter. The Rev. Elam Potter (1742-1794) preached in Enfield, Connecticut. Sybil Pease Potter (1754-1822) was the daughter of Capt. Ephraim Pease and Tabitha Abby. Some time after 1799, she married the widower Rev. Nathaniel Prudden, successor to the Rev. Elam Potter as minister in Enfield.
  - "Potter record": notes on Potter genealogy, after 1865 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Covers the period from 1668 to 1865.
  - Notes on scriptures by the Rev. Elam Potter, 18th century (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Very fragile handwritten notes on Bible passages, most undated.
  - "Extracts from Journal of the Rev. Elam Potter copied from the original manuscript" (Box 2, Folder 14)
    It is unclear when these pencil copies were made and where the original journal is located. The one date included is 1766.
  - "Some circumstances of the sickness and death of the Rev. Elam Potter of Enfield Ct..." (copy?), 1794 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    The Rev. Elam Potter died on Long Island January 5, 1794. This six-page handwritten account was possibly by Potter's son, Elam O. Potter.
  - Letter of Sibyl Pease Potter to Elam O. Potter, 1799, March 6 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Two original sermons by the Rev. Nehemiah Prudden of Enfield, 1796, 1808 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - "Pease record"/ Pease-Prudden family notes, 19th cent. (Box 2, Folder 18)
    The "Pease record," possibly by William Tully, lists the immediate descendents of Captain Ephraim Pease (1720-1801) and includes epitaphs. The Pease-Prudden notes were "copied from Mrs. Prudden's funeral sermon, Feb, 16th 1799" on the back of an 1899 calendar page.
  - Notice of Elam O. Potter's Public House, Wallingford, Connecticut, 1831 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Photographs and miscellany, 4.
  - Photographs of William Tully portraits and of the Tully birthplace in Saybrook, Connecticut. (Box 2, Folder 20)
    The photographs of the home, built by Tully's grandfather ca. 1750, were taken in 1930. Includes negatives.
  - Daguerrotypes and cabinet photographs of children of Dr. William Tully and Mary Potter Tully, 1840s-1880s? (Box 3)
    The envelopes for these items have been numbered.
    - 1. Daguerrotype of William Tully, Jr. (1830-1880), 1861-1865
      In Civil War uniform.
    - 2. Daguerrotype of Elizabeth King Tully, wife of William Tully, Jr.
      She was married to William Tully, son of Dr. William Tully, in 1860.
    - 3-5. Daguerrotypes of Sarah Tully (1815-1901)
    - 6. Daguerrotype of William Tully, Jr.
    - 7. Daguerrotype of William and Elizabeth Lay Tully (1830-1915)
      William and Elizabeth Lay, twins born in 1830, were the last children of Dr. William Tully and Mary Potter Tully. Dr. William Tully's grandmother was Elizabeth Lay.
    - 8. Daguerrotype of William (son) and Elizabeth Lay Tully
    - 9. Daguerrotype probably of Elizabeth Lay Tully
      No cover.
    - 10. Daguerrotype of Hephzibah Tully (1816-1849)
    - 11-12. Daguerrotype of Hephzibah Tully (2 copies)
      Smaller format.
    - Studio cards of Sarah Tully and Elizabeth King Tully
  - Envelope of small keys (Box 3)